<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-jowett-sec-threat-model-constrained-onboarding-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="IETF"
     symRefs="true"
     sortRefs="true"
     tocInclude="true"
     version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Constrained Device Onboarding Security">Security Patterns for Constrained Device Onboarding
over Unauthenticated Local Transports</title>

    <author initials="A." surname="Jowett" fullname="Alan Jowett">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>TBD</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>Security</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Constrained devices are frequently onboarded using local
        transports that provide confidentiality but limited or no peer
        authentication, such as Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) "Just Works"
        pairing or proprietary short-range radios.  While these
        transports are often described as "secure", they do not provide
        device identity guarantees, and naive onboarding designs
        frequently conflate encrypted channels with authenticated peers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document describes common failure modes, threat models, and
        design patterns for bootstrapping trust in constrained devices
        over encrypted but unauthenticated local transports.  It does
        not define a new protocol.  Instead, it documents design
        patterns identified through analysis of constrained-device
        onboarding requirements, including delegation of onboarding
        authority, handling of unavoidable race conditions, bootstrap
        message semantics, and transition to steady-state secure
        communication.  The goal is to provide guidance to designers of
        constrained device onboarding systems and to clarify the
        security properties such systems can and cannot achieve.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>
        Constrained devices such as sensors, actuators, and embedded
        controllers are commonly onboarded into a larger system using
        short-range local transports.  These transports are attractive
        because they are widely available, energy-efficient, and often
        supported by commodity user devices such as smartphones.
      </t>

      <t>
        In practice, many such transports provide confidentiality and
        integrity for messages exchanged between two endpoints, but do
        not provide strong guarantees about the identity of the peer
        during initial contact.  Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) pairing
        using the "Just Works" association model is a common example:
        the resulting link is encrypted, but is vulnerable to active
        man-in-the-middle attacks during pairing and does not provide
        meaningful peer authentication.
      </t>

      <t>
        A recurring design error in onboarding systems is the assumption
        that an encrypted local channel implies that the communicating
        peer is the intended device.  This assumption leads to protocols
        that implicitly rely on properties the transport does not
        provide, resulting in race conditions, identity confusion, or
        brittle security checks layered on top of the channel.
      </t>

      <t>
        At the same time, many real-world systems intentionally accept
        these limitations in exchange for usability, cost, or power-
        consumption constraints.  Rather than attempting to eliminate
        all attacks -- which is often infeasible -- such systems instead
        aim to bound the impact of attacks, ensure recoverability, and
        concentrate trust decisions in components capable of enforcing
        policy.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document captures design patterns and common failure modes
        for constrained-device onboarding systems that operate over
        encrypted but unauthenticated local transports.  It focuses on
        threat-model-first reasoning, explicit separation of bootstrap
        and steady-state security properties, and the use of delegated
        authorities during onboarding.  The document does not propose
        new cryptographic mechanisms or replace existing standards such
        as EDHOC <xref target="RFC9528"/>, OSCORE <xref target="RFC8613"/>,
        or Bluetooth Security Manager Protocol (SMP)
        <xref target="BT-CORE"/>; instead, it complements them by
        clarifying the assumptions required for safe composition.
      </t>

      <t>
        The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
        "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted
        as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
        capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="terminology">
      <name>Terminology</name>

      <t>This document uses the following terms:</t>

      <dl>
        <dt>Authorization Authority:</dt>
        <dd>
          The entity that serves as the root of trust for a deployment.
          It stores device credentials, validates enrollment requests,
          and enforces policy.  Examples include a local gateway, a
          network controller, or a cloud service.
        </dd>

        <dt>Constrained Device:</dt>
        <dd>
          A device with limited processing, memory, power, or
          connectivity resources <xref target="RFC7228"/> that is the
          subject of onboarding.  Before onboarding, the device has no
          pre-existing identity or credentials.
        </dd>

        <dt>Mobile Agent:</dt>
        <dd>
          A user-operated device (typically a smartphone) that mediates
          onboarding on behalf of the authorization authority.  The
          mobile agent holds a revocable credential issued by the
          authority.
        </dd>

        <dt>Local Transport:</dt>
        <dd>
          The communication channel used between the mobile agent and
          the constrained device during onboarding (e.g., BLE, NFC,
          proprietary short-range radio).
        </dd>

        <dt>Steady-State Transport:</dt>
        <dd>
          The communication channel used between the constrained device
          and the authorization authority after onboarding (e.g., a
          low-power radio protocol, Wi-Fi, or cellular).  This may be
          the same as or different from the local transport.
        </dd>

        <dt>Enrollment:</dt>
        <dd>
          The process by which a constrained device is registered with
          the authorization authority and provisioned with credentials
          for steady-state communication.
        </dd>

        <dt>Bootstrap:</dt>
        <dd>
          The initial phase of enrollment during which no shared
          credentials exist between the device and the authority.
        </dd>

        <dt>Steady-State:</dt>
        <dd>
          The operational phase after enrollment, during which the
          device and authority share a symmetric key and can communicate
          with mutual authentication.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scope">
      <name>Scope and Non-Goals</name>

      <section anchor="scope-criteria">
        <name>Scope</name>

        <t>
          This document addresses the design space of onboarding
          protocols for constrained devices that meet ALL of the
          following criteria:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            The device has no factory-provisioned identity (no IDevID,
            no manufacturer certificate, no pre-installed keys).
          </li>
          <li>
            The local transport provides confidentiality (encryption)
            but does not reliably authenticate the peer during initial
            contact.
          </li>
          <li>
            A human operator is involved in the onboarding decision,
            either directly (pressing a button, scanning a code) or
            through a delegated mobile agent.
          </li>
          <li>
            The device is too constrained -- in power, memory, or
            connectivity -- to perform multi-round key exchange
            protocols or maintain persistent TLS/DTLS sessions.
          </li>
          <li>
            An authorization authority serves as the root of trust for
            the deployment and makes all final enrollment decisions.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          The guidance in this document is transport-agnostic.  While
          examples reference BLE and short-range radio protocols, the
          patterns apply to any local transport where encryption does
          not imply authentication.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="non-goals">
        <name>Non-Goals</name>

        <t>This document does NOT:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>Define a new protocol, message format, or wire encoding.</li>
          <li>
            Replace or compete with EDHOC <xref target="RFC9528"/>,
            OSCORE <xref target="RFC8613"/>,
            BRSKI <xref target="RFC8995"/>,
            ACE-OAuth <xref target="RFC9200"/>, or any other IETF
            standard.
          </li>
          <li>
            Provide a formal security proof or verification.  The
            patterns described are based on analysis of onboarding
            requirements and informal threat modeling.
          </li>
          <li>
            Address firmware update security (see
            SUIT <xref target="RFC9019"/>).
          </li>
          <li>
            Address post-onboarding application-layer encryption or
            access control.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="existing-standards">
        <name>Relationship to Existing Standards</name>

        <t>
          Several IETF standards address aspects of constrained-device
          security.  This document addresses a gap that none of them
          individually fill:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>BRSKI <xref target="RFC8995"/>:</dt>
          <dd>
            BRSKI provides automated, voucher-based onboarding but
            requires factory-provisioned X.509 identity certificates
            (IDevID) and a Manufacturer Authorized Signing Authority
            (MASA).  This document addresses systems where devices have
            no factory-provisioned identity and no manufacturer is in
            the trust chain.
          </dd>

          <dt>EDHOC <xref target="RFC9528"/>:</dt>
          <dd>
            EDHOC provides a compact, formally analyzed authenticated
            key exchange.  However, it assumes the communicating parties
            already have a basis for mutual identification (e.g.,
            pre-provisioned credentials or certificates).  This document
            addresses the prior step: how to establish that basis when
            the device is anonymous.
          </dd>

          <dt>ACE-OAuth <xref target="RFC9200"/>:</dt>
          <dd>
            ACE provides authorization for constrained environments
            using OAuth 2.0 semantics.  It assumes the authorization
            server already knows which clients and resource servers
            exist.  This document addresses the bootstrap of that
            knowledge.
          </dd>

          <dt>OSCORE <xref target="RFC8613"/>:</dt>
          <dd>
            OSCORE provides end-to-end object security for CoAP.  It
            assumes keys already exist (from EDHOC, DTLS, or out-of-band
            provisioning).  The patterns in this document are
            complementary: they describe how to establish keys that
            OSCORE (or similar protocols) can subsequently use.
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
          The patterns in this document compose well-understood
          cryptographic primitives and are designed to be compatible
          with adoption of the above standards when the system's
          constraints permit.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="failure-modes">
      <name>Common Failure Modes</name>

      <t>
        This section describes design errors that commonly arise in
        constrained-device onboarding systems that operate over
        encrypted but unauthenticated local transports.
      </t>

      <section anchor="conflating-encryption">
        <name>Conflating Encryption with Authentication</name>

        <t>
          The most common failure mode is treating an encrypted channel
          as proof of peer identity.  When a BLE "Just Works" connection
          is established, the link is encrypted and integrity-protected,
          but the pairing process does not verify which device is at the
          other end.
        </t>

        <t>
          Systems that rely on the encrypted channel for identity make
          an implicit assumption: "because this channel is encrypted,
          the device I am communicating with is the one I intend."  This
          assumption is violated by any active attacker who can initiate
          or intercept a pairing session.
        </t>

        <t>
          The consequence is that credential material transmitted over
          the channel (such as a device key or enrollment payload) may
          be delivered to an attacker rather than the intended device.
          The system has no mechanism to detect this substitution.
        </t>

        <t>
          Mitigation: treat all local transport channels as untrusted
          for identity purposes.  Authenticate at the application layer,
          not the transport layer.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trusting-agent">
        <name>Trusting the Agent to Validate</name>

        <t>
          A second failure mode occurs when the authorization authority
          delegates validation to the mobile agent.  If the authority
          accepts an enrollment request solely because the agent
          submitted it -- without independently verifying the agent's
          credential or the request's integrity -- then a compromised
          or rogue agent can enroll arbitrary devices.
        </t>

        <t>
          Mitigation: the authorization authority <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          independently validate every enrollment request, including
          verification of the agent's credential and any integrity
          checks on the enrollment payload.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="permanent-state">
        <name>Permanent State from Unverified Bootstraps</name>

        <t>
          A third failure mode occurs when a device commits to permanent
          state changes (e.g., erasing a one-time enrollment payload)
          based on an unverified response.  If an attacker can forge an
          enrollment acknowledgement, the device may believe it is
          enrolled when the authority has no record of it.  If the device
          has already erased its enrollment payload, it cannot retry and
          is permanently stranded.
        </t>

        <t>
          Mitigation: defer irreversible state changes until the device
          has independently verified enrollment through normal
          authenticated communication with the authority (see
          <xref target="self-healing"/>).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="threat-model">
      <name>Threat Model Framework</name>

      <t>
        Onboarding protocols that operate over encrypted but
        unauthenticated transports face a specific set of threats that
        differ from those addressed by transport-layer security
        protocols.  This section establishes a framework for
        documenting trust boundaries, assumptions, and explicit
        limitations.
      </t>

      <section anchor="trust-boundaries">
        <name>Trust Boundaries</name>

        <t>
          Systems in this design space typically involve four classes of
          entity, each with distinct trust properties:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Authorization Authority:</dt>
          <dd>
            Root of trust for the deployment.  Stores all device
            credentials, validates all enrollment requests, and enforces
            policy.  Assumed to operate in a controlled environment with
            a protected key store.
          </dd>

          <dt>Constrained Device:</dt>
          <dd>
            Initially has no identity or credentials.  After onboarding,
            authenticated via a unique per-device symmetric key.  Trusted
            for its own data once enrolled, but has no authority over
            other devices.
          </dd>

          <dt>Mobile Agent:</dt>
          <dd>
            Holds a revocable credential issued by the authorization
            authority.  Trusted to initiate enrollment, but the authority
            independently validates every request the agent submits.
          </dd>

          <dt>Local Transport:</dt>
          <dd>
            Provides confidentiality but NOT peer authentication during
            initial contact.  Treated as untrusted for identity purposes.
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
          A critical design principle is that the authorization authority
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> delegate its validation responsibilities
          to the mobile agent.  The agent initiates enrollment; the
          authority decides whether to accept it.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="core-assumptions">
        <name>Core Assumptions</name>

        <t>
          The following assumptions underlie the design patterns in this
          document:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            The authorization authority is operated in a controlled
            environment with a protected key store.
          </li>
          <li>
            Device identity is bound to an embedded symmetric key.
            Physical access to the device is equivalent to key
            compromise.
          </li>
          <li>
            The authority has no persistent outbound connection to
            devices.  Communication is always device-initiated.
          </li>
          <li>
            The mobile agent's authority derives from a credential
            issued by the authorization authority.  The agent generates
            per-device keys and submits enrollment requests, but the
            authority independently validates every request.
          </li>
          <li>
            Compromise of a mobile agent's credential enables
            unauthorized enrollment of new devices, but does not
            affect devices already enrolled (each has an independent
            key).
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="explicit-non-goals">
        <name>Documenting Explicit Non-Goals</name>

        <t>
          Systems operating in this design space <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
          explicitly document which threats they do NOT address.  Common
          examples include:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Confidentiality of Device Data:</dt>
          <dd>
            Many constrained-device protocols authenticate messages (via
            MAC or signature) but do not encrypt payloads.  If the
            application requires confidentiality, it
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be provided at a higher layer.
          </dd>

          <dt>Authorization Authority Compromise:</dt>
          <dd>
            If the authority's key store is compromised, all device keys
            are exposed.  This is an operational security problem, not a
            protocol problem.
          </dd>

          <dt>Physical-Layer Denial of Service:</dt>
          <dd>
            Radio jamming, BLE interference, and similar physical-layer
            attacks are outside the scope of application-layer onboarding
            protocols.
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
          The value of explicitly documenting non-goals is that
          reviewers and auditors can evaluate the system against its
          stated threat model rather than against an implicit (and often
          unrealistic) assumption of universal security.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="bootstrap-vs-steady">
      <name>Bootstrap Versus Steady-State Security</name>

      <t>
        A common source of confusion in constrained-device protocols
        is the failure to distinguish between bootstrap security (the
        properties available during initial onboarding) and steady-
        state security (the properties available after credentials
        have been established).
      </t>

      <section anchor="bootstrap-problem">
        <name>The Bootstrap Problem</name>

        <t>
          During bootstrap, the constrained device has no pre-existing
          credentials.  The onboarding protocol must establish a shared
          secret between the device and the authorization authority,
          using only a local transport that does not authenticate peers.
        </t>

        <t>
          This creates a fundamental asymmetry: the authorization
          authority can verify the mobile agent's identity (via the
          agent's credential), but neither the authority nor the agent
          can cryptographically verify the identity of the constrained
          device during first contact.  The device is, by definition,
          anonymous until onboarding completes.
        </t>

        <t>
          Protocols that attempt to solve this problem by layering
          additional key exchanges on top of the unauthenticated
          transport are solving a different problem.  The core issue is
          not the absence of a key exchange mechanism; it is the absence
          of any prior basis for knowing WHICH device is being
          communicated with.
        </t>

        <t>Effective bootstrap designs therefore focus on:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Concentrating trust decisions in the authorization
            authority.
          </li>
          <li>
            Ensuring that the consequences of a compromised bootstrap
            are bounded and recoverable.
          </li>
          <li>
            Making the human operator's intent (pairing THIS device)
            as explicit as the transport allows.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dual-transport">
        <name>Dual-Transport Architectures</name>

        <t>
          In many constrained-device systems, the local transport used
          for onboarding (e.g., BLE) differs from the steady-state
          transport used for ongoing communication (e.g., a low-power
          radio protocol).  This dual-transport architecture arises
          naturally when:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            The constrained device lacks the resources to maintain a
            persistent BLE connection but can transmit short radio
            frames.
          </li>
          <li>
            The authorization authority is reachable over the steady-
            state transport but not over the local transport.
          </li>
          <li>
            The mobile agent bridges the two transports during
            onboarding but is not involved in steady-state operation.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          In such architectures, the constrained device relays an
          opaque enrollment payload from the local transport to the
          authorization authority over the steady-state transport.  The
          device does not interpret the payload and cannot forge one.
        </t>

        <t>
          The design patterns in <xref target="delegated-authorities"/>
          and <xref target="handling-races"/> accommodate both
          single-transport and dual-transport architectures.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="session-lifecycle">
        <name>Session Lifecycle: A Reference Pattern</name>

        <t>
          This section describes one pattern for session management that
          is well-suited to sleep-based constrained devices.  Other
          patterns exist (e.g., persistent counters with flash wear-
          leveling, epoch-based schemes, or challenge-response per
          message).  The pattern described here optimizes for zero
          persistent state on the device.
        </t>

        <ol>
          <li>
            The device wakes from deep sleep and transmits a session-
            initiation message containing a fresh random nonce
            generated by a hardware random number generator.
          </li>
          <li>
            The authorization authority responds with an authenticated
            message that includes a random starting sequence number,
            binding the response to the device's nonce.
          </li>
          <li>
            All subsequent messages in the session use incrementing
            sequence numbers derived from the authority-assigned
            starting value.
          </li>
          <li>
            The device completes its work and enters deep sleep.
            Neither the device nor the authority persists any replay-
            protection state across sleep cycles.
          </li>
        </ol>

        <t>
          This pattern has two important properties: it requires no
          persistent sequence counters (avoiding flash-wear on
          constrained devices), and it binds each session to a fresh
          random nonce (preventing cross-session replay).
        </t>

        <t>Alternative patterns include:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Persistent monotonic counters stored in flash with wear-
            leveling.  Suitable for devices with sufficient flash
            write budget.
          </li>
          <li>
            Epoch-based schemes where the authority maintains a
            coarse-grained epoch counter and rejects messages from
            previous epochs.
          </li>
          <li>
            Per-message challenge-response, where each message
            includes a fresh challenge.  Suitable for low-frequency
            communication but doubles message count.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="replay-protection">
        <name>Replay Protection Without Persistent State</name>

        <t>
          Traditional replay protection requires at least one party to
          maintain a monotonically increasing counter across sessions.
          This is impractical for devices that deep-sleep between every
          communication cycle and have limited flash-write budgets.
        </t>

        <t>
          The reference pattern described in
          <xref target="session-lifecycle"/> achieves replay protection
          through a combination of:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            A fresh random nonce per session (generated by the
            device).
          </li>
          <li>
            A random starting sequence number per session (assigned
            by the authority in an authenticated response).
          </li>
          <li>
            Strictly incrementing sequence numbers within a session.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          An attacker who replays a captured session-initiation message
          causes the authority to create a new session with a DIFFERENT
          random starting sequence.  The attacker cannot generate valid
          follow-up messages because they lack the device's symmetric
          key to compute the message authentication code.  Replayed
          post-initiation messages from a previous session carry stale
          sequence numbers and are rejected.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="session-replay-tolerable">
        <name>Why Session-Initiation Replay Is Tolerable</name>

        <t>
          Session-initiation messages can themselves be replayed by an
          attacker.  This is tolerable because:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            The attacker cannot forge authenticated follow-up messages
            without the device's symmetric key.
          </li>
          <li>
            The authority creates a new session that simply times out
            with no further activity.  No state is corrupted.
          </li>
          <li>
            The real device's next wake cycle creates an independent
            session unaffected by the phantom.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          The operational cost is limited to a spurious log entry and
          possibly a wasted command to a device that is not listening.
          Both are self-correcting.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="delegated-authorities">
      <name>Delegated Onboarding Authorities</name>

      <section anchor="mobile-agent-pattern">
        <name>The Mobile Agent Pattern</name>

        <t>
          In many deployments, the authorization authority is not
          directly accessible to the constrained device during
          onboarding.  A mobile agent bridges this gap.
        </t>

        <t>The mobile agent pattern involves three phases:</t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Phase 1 - Agent Registration:</dt>
          <dd>
            The mobile agent registers with the authorization authority
            and receives a unique agent credential (e.g., a 256-bit
            pre-shared key).  This is a one-time operation per agent.
          </dd>

          <dt>Phase 2 - Device Provisioning:</dt>
          <dd>
            The mobile agent generates a unique per-device credential,
            constructs an enrollment request authenticated with its
            agent credential, encrypts the request with the authority's
            public key, and transmits both the device credential and the
            encrypted enrollment request to the constrained device over
            the local transport.
          </dd>

          <dt>Phase 3 - Authority Validation:</dt>
          <dd>
            The constrained device relays the encrypted enrollment
            request to the authorization authority over the steady-state
            transport (see <xref target="dual-transport"/>).  The
            authority decrypts the request, verifies the agent's
            authentication, extracts the device credential, and
            registers the device.
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <t>The following diagram illustrates the message flow:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork type="ascii-art"><![CDATA[
  Mobile        Constrained    Authorization
  Agent           Device        Authority
    |                |              |
    |  Phase 1: Agent Registration  |
    |------------------------------>|
    |    agent credential issued    |
    |<------------------------------|
    |                |              |
    |  Phase 2: Device Provisioning |
    |  device_cred + encrypted_req  |
    |--------------->|              |
    |                |              |
    |  Phase 3: Authority Validation|
    |                | relay(enc_req)|
    |                |------------->|
    |                |  enroll_ack  |
    |                |<-------------|
    |                |              |
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          The constrained device acts as a relay for an opaque,
          encrypted payload.  It does not interpret the enrollment
          request and cannot forge one.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="agent-credential-lifecycle">
        <name>Agent Credential Lifecycle</name>

        <t>
          Agent credentials <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> support the following
          operations:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Issuance:</dt>
          <dd>
            The authority generates a unique credential and transmits it
            to the agent over a secured channel.
          </dd>

          <dt>Usage:</dt>
          <dd>
            The agent authenticates every enrollment request with its
            credential.  The authority verifies the credential before
            accepting any request.
          </dd>

          <dt>Revocation:</dt>
          <dd>
            The authority operator can revoke an agent credential at any
            time.  Revoked credentials are retained for audit purposes,
            but all future requests authenticated with the revoked
            credential are rejected.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="trust-properties">
        <name>Trust Properties of Delegation</name>

        <t>
          A well-designed delegation model provides the following
          properties:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Authorization:</dt>
          <dd>
            Only agents holding a valid (non-revoked) credential can
            enroll new devices.
          </dd>

          <dt>Isolation:</dt>
          <dd>
            Each agent has a unique credential.  One agent cannot forge
            requests as another.
          </dd>

          <dt>Auditability:</dt>
          <dd>
            The authority records which agent credential was used to
            enroll each device.
          </dd>

          <dt>Revocability:</dt>
          <dd>
            Revoking an agent credential immediately disables that
            agent's enrollment authority.
          </dd>

          <dt>No Authority Key Exposure:</dt>
          <dd>
            The agent credential is a symmetric pairing credential.  It
            does not grant access to the authority's private key, device
            key database, or other authority state.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="registration-windows">
        <name>Registration Windows</name>

        <t>
          To prevent unauthorized agents from silently enrolling by
          connecting to the authority's local interface, the authority
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> implement a registration window:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Agent registration requests are rejected unless a
            registration window is currently open.
          </li>
          <li>
            The window is opened only by explicit operator action
            (e.g., a physical button press or an authenticated
            administrative command).
          </li>
          <li>
            The window closes automatically after a configurable
            duration (e.g., 120 seconds).
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          This ensures that agent registration requires both possession
          of a valid local transport connection AND contemporaneous
          operator intent.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tofu">
        <name>Trust-On-First-Use for Authority Identity</name>

        <t>
          When a mobile agent connects to an authorization authority
          for the first time, there is typically no pre-existing trust
          anchor.  An attacker could present their own keypair and
          produce a valid response.
        </t>

        <t>
          The recommended approach is Trust-On-First-Use (TOFU) with
          key pinning:
        </t>

        <ol>
          <li>
            The agent establishes that the authority holds a specific
            public key (e.g., via a challenge-response signature, a
            displayed fingerprint, or a QR code).
          </li>
          <li>
            The agent persists the authority's public key and a stable
            authority identifier (pin-on-first-use).
          </li>
          <li>
            Subsequent connections reject any authority presenting a
            different public key.
          </li>
        </ol>

        <t>
          Specific mechanisms for establishing the initial binding
          include:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            Challenge-response: the agent sends a random challenge;
            the authority signs the challenge and its identifier with
            its private key; the agent verifies the signature.
          </li>
          <li>
            Manual verification: the operator compares a fingerprint
            of the authority's public key displayed on both devices.
          </li>
          <li>
            Out-of-band channel: the authority's public key is
            transferred via QR code, NFC tap, or USB.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          For environments requiring stronger assurance than TOFU, the
          operator <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> verify the authority's public
          key fingerprint out-of-band before relying on the pinned key.
        </t>

        <t>
          When using challenge-response, including the authority
          identifier in the signed payload binds the signature to a
          specific authority instance, preventing replay of a signature
          obtained from a different authority.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="handling-races">
      <name>Handling Unavoidable Races</name>

      <t>
        When the local transport does not authenticate peers, certain
        race conditions are inherent and cannot be eliminated by
        protocol design alone.  The goal is to detect, bound, and
        recover from these races rather than pretend they do not
        exist.
      </t>

      <section anchor="mitm-race">
        <name>The Transport-Layer MITM Race</name>

        <t>
          If the local transport uses an unauthenticated pairing model
          (e.g., BLE "Just Works"), an active man-in-the-middle
          attacker can intercept the device credential during
          provisioning.  The attacker can then race the legitimate
          device to submit an enrollment request to the authorization
          authority.
        </t>

        <t>
          This race is INHERENT to the transport model and cannot be
          eliminated without upgrading to an authenticated pairing
          method (e.g., BLE Passkey Entry or Numeric Comparison).
        </t>

        <t>
          Systems that accept this risk <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> implement
          the mitigations described in
          Sections <xref target="one-time-use" format="counter"/>
          through <xref target="self-healing" format="counter"/> to
          bound the impact.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="one-time-use">
        <name>One-Time-Use Registration Payloads</name>

        <t>
          The authorization authority <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> enforce that
          each device identifier can be registered at most once.  If an
          attacker wins the race and registers first using the
          intercepted credential, the duplicate registration attempt
          from the legitimate device is rejected.
        </t>

        <t>This does not prevent the attack, but it ensures that:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            The attacker's registration "burns" the device identifier.
            The attacker cannot register additional devices with the
            same payload.
          </li>
          <li>
            The operator can detect the conflict (two parties claiming
            the same identifier) and investigate.
          </li>
          <li>
            The legitimate device can be factory-reset and
            re-provisioned with a new identifier and credential.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="timestamp-bounded">
        <name>Timestamp-Bounded Replay Windows</name>

        <t>
          Enrollment requests <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include a timestamp
          set by the mobile agent.  The authorization authority
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> reject requests whose timestamps fall
          outside a tolerance window (e.g., +/-24 hours).
        </t>

        <t>
          This limits the window during which a captured enrollment
          request can be replayed, but does not prevent same-day
          attacks.  It is a defense-in-depth measure, not a primary
          mitigation.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="binding-acks">
        <name>Binding Acknowledgements to Requests</name>

        <t>
          When the authorization authority acknowledges a successful
          enrollment, the acknowledgement <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
          cryptographically bound to the specific enrollment request.
          An example pattern is:
        </t>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
   registration_proof = MAC(device_key,
      context_string || enrollment_payload)
]]></artwork>

        <t>where:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>device_key is the newly provisioned per-device key.</li>
          <li>
            context_string is a fixed, protocol-specific string that
            prevents cross-protocol confusion.
          </li>
          <li>
            enrollment_payload is the exact bytes of the encrypted
            enrollment request that was relayed by the device.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          The device verifies the registration_proof before accepting
          the acknowledgement.  This prevents an attacker who
          intercepted the device credential from forging a substitute
          acknowledgement for a different enrollment.
        </t>

        <t>
          Other binding mechanisms (e.g., a signature over a hash of
          the enrollment payload) are equally valid.  The essential
          property is that the acknowledgement is tied to the specific
          enrollment request the device relayed.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="self-healing">
        <name>Self-Healing from Forged Acknowledgements</name>

        <t>
          Even with bound acknowledgements
          (<xref target="binding-acks"/>), an attacker who intercepted
          the device credential over the local transport has all the
          material needed to compute a valid registration_proof.
        </t>

        <t>
          To handle this case, the device <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
          implement deferred payload erasure:
        </t>

        <ol>
          <li>
            After accepting a registration_proof, the device sets a
            "registration complete" flag but does NOT immediately
            erase the enrollment payload.
          </li>
          <li>
            On its next wake cycle, the device attempts normal
            authenticated communication with the authorization
            authority.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the authority responds with a valid authenticated
            message (proving it knows the device's key and has the
            device in its registry), the device erases the
            enrollment payload permanently.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the authority does not respond or responds with an
            authentication failure, the device clears the
            "registration complete" flag and reverts to enrollment
            mode on its next wake cycle.
          </li>
        </ol>

        <t>
          This self-healing behavior ensures that a forged
          acknowledgement does not permanently strand the device in
          a state where it believes it is enrolled but the authority
          has no record of it.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="identity-destruction">
      <name>Identity Destruction and Re-Creation</name>

      <t>
        In many constrained-device systems, the appropriate response
        to key compromise is not key rotation but identity
        destruction.  This is a deliberate design choice, not a
        limitation.
      </t>

      <t>When a device's symmetric key is compromised:</t>

      <ol>
        <li>
          The authorization authority removes the compromised
          device from its registry.
        </li>
        <li>
          The device is factory-reset, which erases: the symmetric
          key (identity), any persistent application state, and any
          resident program or configuration.
        </li>
        <li>
          After reset, the device is inert -- it cannot authenticate
          with any authority and will not execute application logic.
        </li>
        <li>
          The operator re-provisions the device via the normal
          onboarding flow, establishing a new key and a new identity.
        </li>
      </ol>

      <t>
        This destroy-and-recreate model has several advantages over
        in-place key rotation:
      </t>

      <ul>
        <li>
          Simplicity: no key-rotation protocol is needed on the
          constrained device.
        </li>
        <li>
          Clean state: any application state that may have been
          influenced by the attacker is also erased.
        </li>
        <li>
          Auditability: the new identity is a distinct entry in the
          authority's registry, making it clear that a re-provisioning
          event occurred.
        </li>
      </ul>

      <t>
        The cost is operational: an operator must physically interact
        with the device (or be in BLE range) to re-provision it.  For
        systems where this is acceptable, it is a simpler and more
        robust approach than managing key rotation on a constrained
        device.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>

      <t>
        This entire document is about security considerations for
        constrained-device onboarding.  This section highlights
        three cross-cutting concerns.
      </t>

      <section anchor="silent-discard">
        <name>Silent Discard</name>

        <t>
          Protocols operating over unauthenticated transports
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> handle all authentication and integrity
          failures by silent discard.  No error response should be sent
          to the sender.
        </t>

        <t>
          Silent discard prevents information leakage that could
          assist an attacker:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            No indication of whether a key-lookup hint matched any
            known device.
          </li>
          <li>
            No indication of whether a message authentication code
            was close to valid.
          </li>
          <li>
            No indication of whether the authority has an active
            session for the claimed device.
          </li>
          <li>
            No indication of whether the message was syntactically
            well-formed.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>
          Constrained devices operating in sleep-based architectures
          already expect message loss due to radio unreliability.
          Silent discard is therefore compatible with existing retry
          logic (await response or timeout, then retry or sleep).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="key-compromise">
        <name>Key Compromise Containment</name>

        <t>
          The per-device, per-agent keying model described in this
          document provides natural compromise containment:
        </t>

        <dl>
          <dt>Device Key Compromise:</dt>
          <dd>
            Limited to the compromised device.  Other devices are
            unaffected.  The authority removes the compromised device
            from its registry.  The device can be factory-reset and
            re-provisioned with a new key (see
            <xref target="identity-destruction"/>).
          </dd>

          <dt>Agent Credential Compromise:</dt>
          <dd>
            Enables the attacker to forge enrollment requests for new
            devices, but does NOT affect devices already enrolled (each
            has an independent key).  The operator revokes the
            compromised credential; all future requests authenticated
            with it are rejected.  Devices enrolled before revocation
            remain valid unless individually removed.
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <t>
          These properties depend on each device and each agent having
          a unique, independent key.  Shared or derived keys weaken
          containment.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="residual-risks">
        <name>Residual Risks</name>

        <t>
          The patterns in this document reduce but do not eliminate
          risk.  Designers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> acknowledge the
          following residual risks in their threat models:
        </t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            TOFU (<xref target="tofu"/>) is vulnerable to an active
            attacker during first contact between the mobile agent and
            the authorization authority.  Out-of-band verification of
            the authority's public key fingerprint mitigates this risk.
          </li>
          <li>
            BLE "Just Works" pairing (or equivalent unauthenticated
            transport pairing) permits active MITM interception of
            device credentials.  For high-threat environments, an
            authenticated pairing method (Passkey Entry, Numeric
            Comparison, or OOB) is required.
          </li>
          <li>
            The authorization authority is a single point of compromise.
            If its key store is breached, all device keys are exposed.
            Operational security measures (encrypted storage, access
            control, backup) are essential but outside the scope of
            protocol design.
          </li>
          <li>
            The patterns in this document compose well-understood
            cryptographic primitives (ECDH, AEAD, HMAC, CBOR) but have
            not been subjected to formal verification.  Designers who
            require provable security guarantees should consider
            formally analyzed protocols such as
            EDHOC <xref target="RFC9528"/> for the key-exchange
            component, while recognizing that such protocols do not
            address the full onboarding problem described here.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>

      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7228.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8613.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8949.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8995.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9019.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9052.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9200.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9528.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="BT-CORE"
                   target="https://www.bluetooth.com/specifications/specs/core-specification-5-4/">
          <front>
            <title>Bluetooth Core Specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Bluetooth SIG</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2023" month="February"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Version" value="5.4"/>
        </reference>

      </references>
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
